Marat Abdulin

Software Engineer

I'm a skilled software engineer with more than 12 years of experience in web development. During this time I've been working with a variety of technologies and projects. My knowledge covers a broad range of modern full-stack development. I'm proficient in both front-end and back-end technologies.

I'm fond of solving performance issues, working on complex problems and searching for the best solutions that are suitable for both tech and business.



Skills

JavaScript

React, Preact, Vue React env libraries Webpack, Parcel

Jest, Ava, Mocha, Chai, Sinon

NodeJS

Express, Fastify, Nuxt Bolt, Telegraf Sequilize, Mongoose

Ruby

Ruby on Rails, Hanami

Databases

PostgreSQL, MySQL Redis, MongoDB

Clojure

ClojureScript, Reagent, Re-Frame

Other

Front-end performance
Debugging
Mentoring
Team Leading

Contacts

@ marat@esender.me

🔗 <u>esender.me</u>

🞧 <u>esender</u>

in <u>esender</u>

@esender

S <u>esender.me</u>

Languages

English / B1 Russian / native Tatar / native

Work experience

Pitch Software GmbH

Performance Engineer (ClojureScript, Re-frame, Reagent, React)

Pitch is the modern presentation software built for teams.

January 2021 - Present Berlin, Germany

Performance is an important direction of work in Pitch. As the performance team, we are working on different parts of the system, carry out investigations, and finding out what we can do for a better user experience in the performance way. We share our knowledge with other teams and help them improve their codebase as well.

Earnest Inc.

Software Engineer (VanillaJS, Preact, Webpack, Jira, Optimizely, Wordpress)

January 2019 — Present Remote

Earnest is a technology-enabled fintech lender, that offers student loan refinancing and private loans.

My role as front-end developer entails the following:

- Performing page speed optimizations, setting up split tests and configuring a development environment. As well as implementing front-end product features provided by a marketing team.
- Page speed optimizations, speed up page loading.
- Set up webpack configurations, improved development experience. Boosted building speed from 20+ up to less 1s on re-builds.

Student Loan Hero Inc.

March 2018 — January 2019 Remote

Front-end Engineer (React, VanillaJS, Webpack, Jira, Wordpress, CodeShip)

Student Loan Hero is a company that provides guidance and various tools to manage student loans.

My position involved implementing product features, page speed optimizations and working on codebase quality.

- I was working on continuous refactoring the codebase and managed to clean up critical parts of the system.
- Integrated a new building system that improved developer experience and increased the speed of releasing features.
- Worked closely with a separate remote engineering team to effectively complete knowledge transfer after SLH was acquired by LendingTree.

Runtime LLC

March 2016 — March 2018

Kazan, Russia

Front-end Engineer (React, Webpack, Jira, Gemini, Rspec, GitLab CI)

Runtime is a company with various internal products, one of them is a wholesale platform.

Mainly I worked for a single project, a wholesale platform called SitePokupok, which involved implementing new features from scratch using ReactJS, covering codebase with tests, setting up a front-end development environment and mentoring junior FE engineers. My role also included assisting in a small way with other projects, performing bug fixes and front-end development consultations.

- Enhanced performance of initial render complex react components from about 7-8sec up to 1-1.5s.
- Increased test coverage up to 85% using Jest. Introduced screenshot testing using Gemini (Hermione now). Wrote feature tests using rspec.
- Moved building system to Webpack. Established a more efficient development process.

Racoons Group LLC

October 2012 — December 2015 Kazan, Russia

Full-Stack Engineer (Ruby on Rails, AngularJS, Backbone, Express)

Racoons Group was an outsource company that offered a wide range of services.

In this role, I led an engineering team that worked with a top client of the company. My responsibility involved discussing tech questions with the product owner, reviewing developers' code, making decisions.

- Increased test coverage up to 80%
- Sped up SQL gueries, refactored DB structure.
- Worked on the better user experience on the front side.

Freelance

2008 — October 2012

Kazan, Russia

Web Developer (HTML & CSS, Joomla, PHPShop, jQuery)

Education

Kazan National Research Technical University named after September 2007 – July 2011 A.N.Tupolev

Institute of radio-engineering and telecommunications (Bachelor of Engineering and Technology)